1.6 project management business documents.
Now as I said in my spoiler alert from the
previous lesson, project management
business documents are not the same as
project management documents.
I don't know why they have the name is so
similar.
On a project there are 33 project
management documents but they're just two
business documents and they're not treated
the same way.
So this is the project management business
documents.
The project manager needs
to ensure that the project
management approach captures
the intent of business documents.
And that's the purpose of the documents.
And these documents are defined in Table
15.
Pimbach Guide says these two documents are
interdependent and iteratively developed
and maintained throughout the life cycle
of the project.
The project sponsor is generally
accountable for the development and
maintenance of the project business case
document.
The project manager is responsible for
providing recommendations and oversight to
keep the project business case,
project management plan, project charter
and project benefits management plan,
success measures in alignment with one
another and with the goals and objectives
of the organisation.
Project managers should
appropriately tailor the
noted project management
documents for their projects.
Now, stop there for a
moment, you've almost
certainly misunderstood what I just said.
Almost everyone does, and
that misunderstanding can cost
you at least two questions
on the exam, probably more.
We're talking about project business
documents, right?
The PIMBOC guide says project managers
should appropriately tailor the noted
project management documents for their
projects.
Read it carefully.
The PIMBOC guide is not saying project
managers should appropriately tailor the
noted project business documents for their
projects.
The paragraph started talking about
project business documents.
But in the sentence it is talking about
project management documents.
documents, not project
business documents, also
called project management
business documents.
Feeling confused?
Project Manager uses the two project
business documents, the business case and
the benefits management plan, but is not
authorized to change them.
On the project, there are also 33 project
management documents, sometimes just
called project documents and the project
manager will change these.
The paragraph tells us that the project
manager can recommend changes to the
business documents but they're maintained
by the sponsor.
Very important for the exam.
Figure 1.8 illustrates the
interrelationship of these critical
business documents and the needs
assessments as well as an approximation of
the life cycle of these various documents
against the generic life cycle.
One, project business case.
The PIMBOC guide says the project business
case is a documented economic feasibility
study used to establish the validity of
the benefits of a selected component,
lacking sufficient definition
and that is used as a basis for
the authorization of further
project management activities.
The business case lists the objectives and
the reasons for.
or project initiation.
It helps measure the
project success at the end
of the project, against
the project objectives.
The business case is a
project business document
that is used throughout
the project lifecycle.
The business case may be used before the
project initiation, it may result in a go,
no-go decision for the project.
A needs assessment often precedes the
business case.
The needs assessment involves
understanding business goals and
objectives and issues and opportunities
and recommending proposals to address them.
The results of the needs assessment may be
summarised in the business case document.
The process of defining a business need,
analysing situation, making
recommendations and
defining evaluation criteria
is applicable to any
organisation's projects.
A business case may include document in
the following.
And in the exam, you may be asked a
question on the following headings,
plus of course all of the previous uses of
the business case.
So started with business needs.
Determination of what is prompting the
need for action.
Why are we doing this?
Do we need to fix something?
Do we need to increase sales?
Do we need to comply with legislation,
for example?
Situational statement
documenting the business
problem or opportunity to be addressed.
including the value to be delivered to the
organisation.
Was this a specific problem, opportunity
or mandate that is driving this?
Identification of stakeholders affected
and identification of the scope.
This is not the scope statement initially,
it's just the main deliverables but this
will be progressively elaborated during
the project to form the scope statement.
Analysis of the situation.
So far we've said that perhaps,
Perhaps we can see an opportunity to
increase sales by developing a better type
of mouse trap.
We have listed the main affected
stakeholders.
Please note that mice are not considered
stakeholders even though they will be
perfected by the project or perceive
themselves to be affected by the project.
Now we need to properly
analyse the situation rather than
just rushing ahead in case
we end up in a trap ourselves.
The analysis might
include identification of
organisational strategies,
goals and objectives.
Identification of root
causes of the problem
or main contributors to the opportunity.
Gap analysis of capabilities
needed for the project
versus existing capabilities
of the organisation.
Identification of known risks.
Identification of critical success
factors.
Identification of
decision criteria by which,
the various courses of
action can be assessed.
Examples of criteria categories used for
analysis of a situation are required.
This is a criterion that
must be fulfilled, e.g.,
the mouse trap must
be able to kill mice swiftly.
Desired, this is a criterion that we would
really like to have fulfilled,
but it is not absolutely
essential, e.g., we prefer
it if the trap did not
require food as be it.
The next one is optional.
This is a criterion that is not essential.
Fulfillment of this criterion may become a
differentiator between alternative courses
of action, and that's an
important note for the examination,
that although it's optional,
we don't actually need it.
If there's nothing else to choose on,
we may use that to choose the project.
E.g.
the mousetrap won't harm
white mice because we
don't want pet mice to
get harmed by our trap.
That's an option.
We don't need to have it.
It would be nice.
Identification of a set of
options to be considered
for addressing the business
problem or opportunity.
The most commonly used three options are
do nothing.
This is referred to as the business as
usual option.
Selection of this option results in
the project not being authorised, i.e.
, what happens if we don't
develop a new match trap?
2.
The minimum work possible to address the
problem or opportunity.
The minimum may be established by
identifying the set of documented criteria
that are key at address the problem or
opportunity.
The next option is do
more than the minimum work
possible to address the
problem or opportunity.
This option meets the
minimum set of criteria
and some or all of the
other documented criteria.
It may be more than one of these options
documented in the business case.
Next is the recommendation.
We are considering the reasons for
starting a project.
We vandalise the situation in detail and
now we have considered options.
Now it's the time to to
pull all this information
together and recommend
what the organisation should do.
A statement of the recommended option to
pursue in the project, e.g.
we will develop an electric marsh trap,
which is artificial intelligence and
machine learning
capabilities, so it can constantly
evolve to become an
even better marsh trap.
Items too include, and the statement may
include analysis results for the potential
options, constraints,
assumptions, risks and
dependencies for potential
options, and success measures.
An implementation approach
that may include milestones,
dependencies and
roles and responsibilities.
That brings us to evaluation.
Statement describing the plan for measuring
benefits the project will deliver.
This will cover not just the benefits
realized if any during the project.
For example, during testing, the project
will probably be.
reduce the number of mice in the
organisation.
But we also want to look at benefits when
the project has moved into operation.
The business case document provides the
basis to measure success and progress
throughout the project
lifecycle by comparing the results
with the objectives and the
identified success criteria.
Two, the project benefits management plan.
The project benefits management plan is
the document that the describes how and
when the benefits of the project will be
delivered.
And describes the mechanisms it should be
in place to measure those benefits.
For example, if the project is intended to
enable the service test to resolve
customer problems 20%
faster on average, what does
this actually mean and
how can it be measured?
Pimbock Guide says a project benefit is
defined as the outcome of actions,
behaviours, products, services or results
that provide value to the sponsoring
organisation as well as to the project's
intended beneficiaries.
Development of the Benefits Management
Plan begins early in the lifecycle with
the definition of the target benefits to
be realised.
The Benefits Management
Plan describes key elements of
the benefits and may include
documenting the function.
following.
Firstly, the target benefits, e.g.
the expected tangible
and intangible value to
be gained by the
implementation of the project.
Financial value is
expressed as net present
value, which you'll
cover later in the course.
Strategic alignment, e.g.
how well the project benefits align to the
business strategies of the organisation.
The time frame for realising benefits,
e.g.
benefits by phase, short-term,
long-term and ongoing.
Benefits owner, for example, the
accountable person to monitor,
record and report
realized benefits throughout
the time frame established in the plan.
And often it's what we
would call one of the
business users would
be involved in doing that.
Someone who actually is going to use the
products, or rather that their staff is
going to be using the products in the best
one to check it out.
Next one is the met.
i.e.
the measures to be used to show benefits
realized, direct measures
and indirect measures.
This is a very important one.
Benefits must be measurable.
Because if you can't measure them, how
can you tell if the project was a success?
In the example of the service
desk, I said the customer
problems were to be solved
20% faster on average.
But if I had just said the service desk
has to solve customer problems faster,
you can't measure this and so you can't
tell if the project actually achieved it.
Next is assumptions, e.g.
factors expected to be in place or to be
in evidence and risks.
Example, risks for realization of the
benefits.
Developing the benefits management plan
makes use of the data and information
documented in the business case and needs
assessment.
For example, the cost benefit analysis
recorded in the documents illustrate the
estimate of cost compared with the value
of the benefits realized by the project.
The Benefits Management Plan and project
management plan include a description of
how the business value
resulting from the project
becomes part of the
organization's ongoing operation.
including the metrics to be used.
The metrics provide
verification of the business
value and validation
of the project success.
Just a reminder, benefits need
to be measurable otherwise
you don't know for sure
that you've achieved them.
Number three, the project charter and
project management plan.
For the examination, please remember the
project charter is defined as a document
issued by the project sponsor It formally
authorises the existence of a project and
provides a project
manager with the authority to
apply organizational
resources to project activities.
We cover this more in integration
management.
The project management plan is defined as
a document that describes how the project
will be executed, monitored and
controlled.
There are 33 project documents in a
project which are used to manage the
project, but they are not part of the
project management plan.
Number four, project success measures.
Please read project success measures in
the project guide page 34.
It's a very simple section to understand.
It's just really a very long list.
That brings us to the end of
project management business
documents and also to the end
of foundational elements module.
At the start of this module, I promise
that you'd learn important information.
from it and I've no doubt that you have.
The next module is 2.0 environments in
which projects operate.
Please read the corresponding chapter in
the Poonback Guide before watching the
video so that you can operate well in the
examination environment.